<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Codemeta Archives - Software Heritage</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/tag/codemeta/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/tag/codemeta/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 15:10:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/cropped-swh-logo-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Codemeta Archives - Software Heritage</title>
	<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/tag/codemeta/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>CodemetaR Author streamlines software metadata updates</title>
		<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/06/18/codemetar-author-streamlines-software-metadata-updates/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicole Martinelli]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 14:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Codemeta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CodemetaR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[metadata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[R]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tutorial]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.softwareheritage.org/?p=46150</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This tutorial covers using the codemetar R package to generate universal Codemeta JSON files.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/06/18/codemetar-author-streamlines-software-metadata-updates/">CodemetaR Author streamlines software metadata updates</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>By Frédéric Santos, Software Heritage Ambassador</em></p>



<p>Think of software metadata as the essential ID card for any software package. It&#8217;s that structured information that tells you all about the program: its name, version, who made it, what license it uses, what other software it needs to run, and other important details. For R packages specifically, this means information about what the package actually does, which other R packages it depends on, the minimum R version it requires, and even its intended purpose.&nbsp;</p>



<p>To cut through the tangle of diverse, language-specific metadata formats, the <a href="https://codemeta.github.io/">Codemeta</a> project stepped in. Its mission is to standardize and improve the sharing of software metadata, offering a universal schema (built on a JSON-like syntax) to describe software. This common approach helps turn metadata into a format that can easily &#8220;cross-work&#8221; between many different programming languages, making software easier to discover, cite, and reproduce.</p>



<p>This post offers an overview of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TS1UjPspVkA">14-minute video tutorial</a>, highlighting how the <a href="https://github.com/ropensci/codemetar">codemetar R package </a>simplifies generating and updating this crucial Codemeta metadata for your R packages.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Seamless update software metadata process with CodemetaR Author: Frédéric Santos, SWH Ambassador" width="660" height="371" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TS1UjPspVkA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Why bother with organized software metadata?</strong></p>



<p>Keeping your software metadata organized and fresh isn&#8217;t just a nice-to-have; it&#8217;s critical for several reasons. If you&#8217;re a researcher, for instance, you know how vital it is for your analyses to be reproducible by others. Accurate software metadata is key here, since it specifies the exact software versions and dependencies that people need to replicate your work precisely. It also tells authors how to properly cite the software they&#8217;ve used in their articles, which is very important. But beyond just reproducibility and citation, well-structured metadata acts like a beacon for discoverability. Search engines can find your software more easily, linking it to relevant keywords. Even popular software repositories like GitHub would be a nightmare to navigate without good metadata. So, truly, any software developer – and R developers are definitely included – should pay close attention to how they specify metadata in their packages.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The R-specific way and its bottleneck</h2>



<p>When you build an R package, the standard, built-in way to define all this necessary metadata is through the DESCRIPTION file. This file is where you&#8217;ll find essential fields like Title, Description, Author, License, and Imports. These details are crucial for users to grasp the package’s purpose and requirements, and they help external tools or repositories reference your package better. You can even generate a DESCRIPTION file template using R&#8217;s built-in functions or the devtools package. Sometimes, you might also find richer, though less structured, info in a README file.</p>



<p>But here&#8217;s the catch: the DESCRIPTION file has a very specific R-centric format or syntax. This becomes a real headache because other programming languages have their own unique ways of handling package metadata. Take a <a href="https://julialang.org/">Julia</a> package, for example; it might use a Project.toml file. Or an <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs">Emacs Lisp</a> package, where metadata lives right in the header of its main file. The syntax and structure of these files are vastly different from R&#8217;s DESCRIPTION file. This language-specific approach creates a big problem for automatically collecting software metadata across different ecosystems, as each language demands a specific process for data extraction. This challenge directly impacts search engines, software archives, and repositories that aim to gather and organize information about a wide variety of software projects.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><a href="https://codemeta.github.io/codemeta-generator/"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/codemeta-generator-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-41700" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/codemeta-generator-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/codemeta-generator-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/codemeta-generator-768x433.jpg 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/codemeta-generator-1536x866.jpg 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/codemeta-generator-2048x1154.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure></div>


<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Enter Codemeta: The Universal Translator for Software Metadata</h2>



<p>To tackle this tangled mess of different metadata formats, the Codemeta project stepped in. Its main goal? To offer a single, universal format for describing software that isn&#8217;t tied to any specific programming language. Codemeta achieves this by using a common schema based on a JSON-like syntax. By creating a codemeta.json file, developers can transform their software metadata into a format that can easily &#8220;cross-work&#8221; across many different programming languages. This standardized approach is a game-changer for improving software discoverability, reproducibility, and citation.</p>



<p>You&#8217;d typically place a codemeta.json file at the very root of your R package directory, right alongside your DESCRIPTION file. Since it’s not part of the standard R package build process and doesn&#8217;t inherently belong to the R universe, you can just add it to your .Rbuildignore list. This ensures it gets skipped when your package is built, preventing any issues.&nbsp; While the JSON format used by codemeta.json files is powerful, it can be quite heavy, challenging for humans to read, and even harder to type manually.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The hassle of manual codemeta.json management</h2>



<p>Given how complex JSON can be, trying to manually create or update codemeta.json files is, frankly, impractical. Sure, there are some automatic generation options, like websites provided by the Codemeta project team, where you fill in fields to get your JSON file. There&#8217;s even a newer version (a fork) of the Codemeta generator that can auto-fill fields if you just give it a GitHub or GitLab URL. These are nice, but still require you to manually update the codemeta.json file every time you release a new version of your R package. This opens the door to forgetting to update the file, leaving you with outdated codemeta.json information. Clearly, there&#8217;s a need for a more integrated, automated solution, especially for developers who frequently update their packages.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Enter codemetar: Your R Package metadata<strong> sidekick</strong></h2>



<p>This is precisely where the <a href="https://github.com/ropensci/codemetar">codemetar </a>package steps in. The codemetar package is designed to help R developers effortlessly generate, parse, modify, and update codemeta.json files for their R packages. It’s readily available on CRAN, so you can install it with the usual install.packages(&#8220;codemeta&#8221;) command.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/codemeta_tutorial-1.png"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="578" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/codemeta_tutorial-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46165" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/codemeta_tutorial-1.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/codemeta_tutorial-1-300x169.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/codemeta_tutorial-1-768x434.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Metadata from the DESCRIPTION file automatically populates this codemeta.json file</em>.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The real magic of codemetar lies in its ability to automatically pull relevant information from your R package&#8217;s DESCRIPTION file and seamlessly convert it into the Codemeta JSON format. A simple function call like write_codemeta() is all it takes to extract all that useful metadata from your DESCRIPTION file and pop it into a new codemeta.json file. What’s more, codemetar can even dig into your README file to extract extra metadata, like badges showing continuous integration services or minimum R version requirements. And here’s a neat little trick: codemetar automatically adds the generated codemeta.json file to your .Rbuildignore file, ensuring it never messes with your R package build process.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Painless updates and CRAN Integration</h2>



<p>A big benefit of using codemetar is how it simplifies keeping your package’s metadata fresh throughout its entire development lifecycle. This is important when you&#8217;re pushing out new versions, bringing in new contributors, or even changing where your development is hosted (like moving from GitHub to GitLab). And for those of you already using devtools::release() to push your packages to CRAN, get ready for some truly seamless integration. When this function runs to submit a new package version, it automatically checks if your codemeta.json file is up-to-date and matches the metadata in your DESCRIPTION file. If there’s a mismatch, devtools::release() will give you a warning. This effectively acts as a safety net, ensuring you’ll never forget to update your codemeta.json file when you&#8217;re submitting to CRAN.</p>



<p>In a nutshell, the codemetar R package streamlines how R developers manage their package metadata. By offering an easy, automated way to create and maintain codemeta.json files, codemetar not only boosts the discoverability and citation of R packages but also helps ensure their reproducibility by standardizing metadata in a universally understood format.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">About Frédéric Santos</h3>



<p>Frédéric Santos is a data analyst at <a href="https://www.cnrs.fr/">CN</a><a href="https://www.cnrs.fr/en">R</a><a href="https://www.cnrs.fr/">S</a>, the French National Centre for Scientific Research. His programming expertise spans R, Julia, Bash, and Emacs Lisp. As an ambassador, his fields of expertise include machine learning, notebooks, and reproducible research. You can explore his projects on <a href="https://gitlab.com/f-santos">GitLab</a> and <a href="https://github.com/frederic-santos">GitHub</a> as well as his <a href="https://f-santos.gitlab.io/about.html">website</a>. He&#8217;s been a <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2023/12/05/ambassador-frederic-santos/">Software Heritage Ambassador since 2023</a>. </p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/06/18/codemetar-author-streamlines-software-metadata-updates/">CodemetaR Author streamlines software metadata updates</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Software Heritage Citation Feature: Addressing researcher needs</title>
		<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/05/07/software-heritage-citation-feature/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Morane Gruenpeter]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 14:35:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[citation feature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[citations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[code citation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[code credit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Codemeta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[software citation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.softwareheritage.org/?p=25758</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Software Heritage now offers built-in citation support, a significant step in acknowledging software as a legitimate research output.  </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/05/07/software-heritage-citation-feature/">Software Heritage Citation Feature: Addressing researcher needs</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Software is essential in academic research—whether as a tool for data analysis, a research output, or even the very object of study. A truly Open Science ecosystem requires giving software the same attention and recognition as publications and datasets. In academia, citations are the currency of credit.</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div>When we began working on Software Heritage in 2014, interest in software as a research outcome steadily grew, driven in part by increasing awareness of software’s critical role in tackling the reproducibility crisis. One area that quickly drew attention was software citation, which culminated in the 2016 publication of the <a href="https://peerj.com/preprints/2169/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FORCE11 &#8220;Software citation principles.&#8221;</a><del><br></del></div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div>Nearly a decade later, software citation continues to evolve, thanks to the ongoing efforts of initiatives like the <a href="https://force11.org/group/software-citation-working-group/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noreferrer noopener" data-sourcepos="6:305-6:410">FORCE11 Software Citation Working Group (WG)</a> and the joint <a href="https://www.rd-alliance.org/groups/rdaforce11-software-source-code-identification-wg/members/all-members/">RDA/FORCE11/ReSA Software Identification Working Group (WG)</a>.</div>
<div>
<p dir="auto" data-sourcepos="8:1-8:265">Following <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/repositories/managing-your-repositorys-settings-and-features/customizing-your-repository/about-citation-files">GitHub’s</a> lead, Software Heritage now has built-in citation support. This is a big step towards finally recognizing software as a real research output.</p>
<p dir="auto" data-sourcepos="8:1-8:265">This blog post gives a quick rundown of the important news and how Software Heritage is shaking things up for citing software. We&#8217;re tackling a problem that&#8217;s been around for ages and offering a fix.</p>
</div>
<h2>Citation made easy with Software Heritage</h2>
<div>With this new feature, researchers, users, and readers can now easily generate and copy a BibTeX citation directly from Software Heritage into their <code data-start="259" data-end="265">.bib</code> files.</div>
<div>
<p class="" data-start="276" data-end="436">Citing a specific software version—or even a precise code fragment—is just as simple: select the version or highlight the lines of code, and you&#8217;re ready to go.</p>
<p class="" data-start="1597" data-end="1782">Before diving deeper into the challenge of credit, it’s helpful to understand what’s already achievable using Software Heritage’s existing tools for software reference and preservation.</p>
<p class="" data-start="1784" data-end="1873">The universal archive of Software Heritage allows researchers and developers to:</p>
<ol>
<li class="" data-start="1875" data-end="1983">
<p class="" data-start="1877" data-end="1983">Prepare their repositories with key metadata files (<code data-start="1929" data-end="1938">AUTHORS</code>, <code data-start="1940" data-end="1948">README</code>, <code data-start="1950" data-end="1959">LICENSE</code>, <code data-start="1961" data-end="1976">codemeta.json</code>, etc.)</p>
</li>
<li class="" data-start="1984" data-end="2085">
<p class="" data-start="1986" data-end="2085">Trigger archival using the <a href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/save/">Save Code Now</a> interface, the browser extension, or a webhook</p>
</li>
<li class="" data-start="2086" data-end="2207">
<p class="" data-start="2088" data-end="2207">Obtain a Software Hash Identifier (<a href="https://docs.softwareheritage.org/devel/swh-model/persistent-identifiers.html">SWHID</a>)—a persistent, verifiable reference to a specific version or component. With the new citation feature, you can generate a ready-to-use BibTeX citation directly from the archived object, offering a more robust and reliable alternative to citing a forge URL.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
<div>
<p><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-from-2024-11-29-10-08-40.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-43504" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-from-2024-11-29-10-08-40.png" alt="citation-box" width="1533" height="791" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-from-2024-11-29-10-08-40.png 1533w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-from-2024-11-29-10-08-40-300x155.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-from-2024-11-29-10-08-40-1024x528.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-from-2024-11-29-10-08-40-768x396.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1533px) 100vw, 1533px" /></a></p>
</div>
<div>For details on how to cite, check the <a class="" href="https://docs.softwareheritage.org/devel/architecture/citation.html" target="_new" rel="noopener" data-start="152" data-end="220">Software Heritage documentation</a>. It describes how the system uses the software&#8217;s internal data to generate a citation you can export.</div>
<div>
<p class="" data-start="300" data-end="547">Software Heritage can automatically generate a BibTeX citation using the intrinsic metadata archived from a software repository. This metadata is typically sourced from either a <code data-start="482" data-end="497">codemeta.json</code> or a <code data-start="503" data-end="517">citation.cff</code> file found in the repository.</p>
<p class="" data-start="1197" data-end="1434">To make citing code easier, users can embed a specific version or fragment of code directly into webpages using iframes. A simple Web UI endpoint is provided for this purpose. Here’s an example:</p>
<p><iframe style="width: 100%; height: 500px; border: 1px solid rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.125);" src="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/browse/embed/swh:1:dir:bc7ddd62cf3d72ffdc365e1bf2dea6eeaa44e185;origin=https://github.com/rdicosmo/parmap;visit=swh:1:snp:8ddca416836fbbc2a7704c69db38739bef6b6cae;anchor=swh:1:rev:ecd3744ed558da4ea2bf9eb87b80b8949f417126/"><br /></iframe></p>
</div>
<hr>
<h2>A long, intertwined journey</h2>
<div>The <a href="https://peerj.com/preprints/2169/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Software Citation Principles&#8221;</a> FORCE11 paper highlights four key motivations for citing software:</div>
<ol>
<li>Credit</li>
<li>Understanding research fields</li>
<li>Discovering software</li>
<li>Reproducibility</li>
</ol>
<p>These goals are crucial, but not exactly straightforward. To make them happen, we need to look at the practical parts of &#8220;software citation.&#8221; We&#8217;re drawing on the guidance from the European Open Science Cloud (EOSC) <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2020/10/23/towards-an-open-architecture-of-scholarly-infrastructures-for-research-software/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://doi.org/10.2777/28598&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1622488651684000&amp;usg=AFQjCNFQHvFEdj9q3WyUFgxUpLiB95_UlA">report</a> on Scholarly Infrastructures for Research Software (December 2020), full report <a href="https://op.europa.eu/en/publication-detail/-/publication/145fd0f3-3907-11eb-b27b-01aa75ed71a1/language-en">here</a>. The 94-page report outlines practical recommendations to improve the current landscape by building on and connecting existing infrastructures.</p>
<div>
<h3>Breaking down software citation components</h3>
</div>
<div>
<div>It might seem like &#8220;software citation&#8221; is easy – just one more thing to list in your bibliography. But actually, the concept brings up at least four distinct and equally important points:</div>
<ul>
<li class="" data-start="1111" data-end="1194">
<p class="" data-start="1113" data-end="1194"><strong data-start="1113" data-end="1125">Archival</strong>: Ensuring long-term preservation and accessibility to the source code</p>
</li>
<li class="" data-start="1195" data-end="1286">
<p class="" data-start="1197" data-end="1286"><strong data-start="1197" data-end="1210">Reference</strong>: Accurately identifying the exact version used, to ensure reproducibility</p>
</li>
<li class="" data-start="1287" data-end="1370">
<p class="" data-start="1289" data-end="1370"><strong data-start="1289" data-end="1304">Description</strong>: Capturing structured, well-curated metadata about the software</p>
</li>
<li class="" data-start="1371" data-end="1448">
<p class="" data-start="1373" data-end="1448"><strong data-start="1373" data-end="1383">Credit</strong>: Acknowledging all contributors involved in the software project</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Among these, the most complex and often debated issue is credit— how credit can be given? What &#8220;thing&#8221; do we want to cite?</p>
<h3>Artifacts granularity &#8211; SWHIDs in citations</h3>
<p class="" data-start="2431" data-end="2685">Software is often difficult to cite precisely due to its layered and modular structure. Even small projects usually have several parts, so citing a specific version—or even a specific commit—might be needed for reproducibility or clarity.</p>
<p class="" data-start="2687" data-end="2831">While DOIs are widely used to cite publications and datasets, software presents different challenges. As Software Heritage co-founder Roberto Di Cosmo and co-authors note:</p>
<blockquote data-start="2832" data-end="2965">
<p class="" data-start="2834" data-end="2965">“[…] we need identifiers that are not only unique and persistent but also intrinsically support integrity.” (<a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3183558">Di Cosmo et al., 2018)</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p class="" data-start="2967" data-end="3317">This means relying not on a centralized registry, but on cryptographic techniques. SWHIDs meet this need by being computed directly from the content of the digital object, using cryptographically secure hashing algorithms. Anyone with a copy of the object can independently verify the identifier, making SWHIDs uniquely resilient and trustworthy.</p>
<div id="attachment_43507" style="width: 3014px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/SWHID-granularity.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-43507" class="wp-image-43507 size-full" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/SWHID-granularity.png" alt="" width="3004" height="1844" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/SWHID-granularity.png 3004w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/SWHID-granularity-300x184.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/SWHID-granularity-1024x629.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/SWHID-granularity-768x471.png 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/SWHID-granularity-1536x943.png 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/SWHID-granularity-2048x1257.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 3004px) 100vw, 3004px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-43507" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Research Data Alliance/FORCE11 Software Source Code Identification WG, 2020, https://doi.org/10.15497/RDA00053</em></p></div>
<h3>Why is software attribution so hard?</h3>
<div>
<div dir="ltr" data-smartmail="gmail_signature">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<p>Sometimes, the list of individuals involved in a software project is very long, so long that it&#8217;s not feasible to include everyone directly in a citation. As a result, a common practice has emerged: attributing authorship to the project team or collective entity. For instance, the software record might list “The Givaro group” as the author.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Givaro-group-example-e1687467908870.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-35714 size-full" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Givaro-group-example-e1687467908870.png" alt="" width="1766" height="966" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Givaro-group-example-e1687467908870.png 1766w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Givaro-group-example-e1687467908870-300x164.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Givaro-group-example-e1687467908870-1024x560.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Givaro-group-example-e1687467908870-768x420.png 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Givaro-group-example-e1687467908870-1536x840.png 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1766px) 100vw, 1766px" /></a></p>
<div>
<div>
<div dir="ltr" data-smartmail="gmail_signature">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<h4>How should credit be given?</h4>
<p>Just like with articles where the writers are the authors, we usually assume the developers of code are software authors. However, like everything else about software, it&#8217;s more complicated than it looks. Software projects involve many different roles, so the simple term &#8220;author,&#8221; even with &#8220;contributor&#8221; added, definitely doesn&#8217;t cover everyone involved. One paper,&nbsp; &#8220;<a href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-02135891">Attributing and Referencing (Research) Software: Best Practices and Outlook From Inria,</a>&#8221; identifies nine key roles, similar to what the <a href="https://casrai.org/credit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CRediT</a> system does for research articles, based on extensive real-world experience. Other communities have also identified the need for distinguishing different software roles. (See the <a href="https://sdruskat.net/software-authorship/">SORTÆD</a> example for a Software Role Taxonomy and Authorship Definition.)</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h4>But is this approach sufficient?</h4>
<p class="" data-start="495" data-end="826">The answer largely depends on the infrastructure behind the citation, specifically, whether it can maintain the relationships between the software and the people who contributed to it. A named group is only meaningful if it can be linked to individual members, their roles, and the context of their contributions.</p>
<p class="" data-start="828" data-end="1208">Here, Software Heritage offers a solid base. While citations may remain concise, the underlying metadata, especially when enriched with structured information like <code data-start="1010" data-end="1025">codemeta.json</code> or <code data-start="1029" data-end="1043">citation.cff</code>can hold detailed attribution records. These can include individual contributors, their specific roles, and even ORCID identifiers to ensure long-term traceability.</p>
<p class="" data-start="1210" data-end="1386">This layered approach balances concise citation with rich, machine-readable credit, helping infrastructure bridge the gap between recognition and practical constraints.</p>
<p class="" data-start="1388" data-end="1677">Ultimately, giving credit in software requires more than just a name on a list—it requires context, clarity, and systems that respect the complexity of collaborative work. And that’s exactly what we aim to support through Software Heritage’s evolving citation tools and metadata practices.</p>
<h3>Finally, the <code data-start="123" data-end="134">@software</code> type in BibTeX gets long-awaited improvements</h3>
</div>
<div>
<p class="" data-start="94" data-end="329">The <code data-start="229" data-end="240">@software</code> entry type in BibTeX has been around for a long time, but it was just a placeholder, treated like the @misc entry. In 2020 it was finally enriched with long-awaited metadata for software&nbsp; — a major milestone for software citation in academic publishing.</p>
<p class="" data-start="331" data-end="524">Thanks to the <code data-start="345" data-end="364">biblatex-software</code> package available on CTAN, you can now cite software with much greater precision using four dedicated entry types that reflect different levels of granularity:</p>
<ul data-start="526" data-end="880">
<li class="" data-start="526" data-end="587">
<p class="" data-start="528" data-end="587"><code data-start="528" data-end="539">@software</code> — for general references to computer software</p>
</li>
<li class="" data-start="588" data-end="673">
<p class="" data-start="590" data-end="673"><code data-start="590" data-end="607">@softwaremodule</code> — for citing a specific module within a larger software project</p>
</li>
<li class="" data-start="674" data-end="749">
<p class="" data-start="676" data-end="749"><code data-start="676" data-end="694">@softwareversion</code> — for referencing a particular version of a software</p>
</li>
<li class="" data-start="750" data-end="880">
<p class="" data-start="752" data-end="880"><code data-start="752" data-end="767">@codefragment</code> — for pinpointing a specific code fragment, such as an algorithm or a key function within a program or library</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p class="" data-start="882" data-end="1091">Here’s an example of how this can be implemented using the <code data-start="941" data-end="960">biblatex-software</code> package. The sample below (entries 2, 6, and 7) demonstrates how tags distinguish between software projects and specific releases:</p>
</div>
<blockquote>
<div>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;<i>[Rp] Reproducing and replicating the OCamlP3l experiment</i></div>
<div>&nbsp; &nbsp; ReScience C, 6 (1), 2020&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4041602" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4041602&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1622488651684000&amp;usg=AFQjCNHGOalYBjBsDdLSUQEHuQDSTuwVnQ">https://doi.org/10.5281/<wbr>zenodo.4041602</a></div>
</blockquote>
<div><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/biblatex-software-references-examples.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-35720" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/biblatex-software-references-examples.png" alt="" width="625" height="352" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/biblatex-software-references-examples.png 1280w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/biblatex-software-references-examples-300x169.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/biblatex-software-references-examples-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/biblatex-software-references-examples-768x432.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px" /></a></div>
<h3>The road ahead&#8230; and a word of caution</h3>
<p class="" data-start="166" data-end="528">In short, we&#8217;ve achieved real progress on several fundamental parts of software citation. Now, you can archive, properly reference, and even directly cite any piece of source code from the universal archive. A standard for describing software is taking shape, and there’s growing experience and expertise in curating this metadata and navigating the nuanced challenge of assigning appropriate credit.</p>
<p class="" data-start="530" data-end="741">We hope these emerging best practices will be adopted by stakeholders beyond Europe, where <a href="https://doi.org/10.2777/28598" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the EOSC SIRS report</a> and the <a href="https://faircore4eosc.eu/eosc-core-components/eosc-research-software-apis-and-connectors-rsac">FAIRCORE4EOSC</a> project have laid crucial groundwork, but also globally.</p>
<div>
<div>
<div dir="ltr" data-smartmail="gmail_signature">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">
<p class="" data-start="743" data-end="1122">Nevertheless, it&#8217;s important to acknowledge that the question of &#8220;how credit is assigned&#8221; remains a highly sensitive and intricate challenge, an issue well documented by the <a href="https://sfdora.org/">DORA declaration</a> and echoed in earlier reflections from the computer science community.</p>
<p class="" data-start="1124" data-end="1367">We must avoid repeating these errors with software. The risks could actually be even greater. Simply relying on citation counts for credit could unintentionally harm how we see the value of different software contributions.</p>
<p class="" data-start="1369" data-end="1411">As the <em data-start="1376" data-end="1387">EOSC SIRS</em> report wisely cautions:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<blockquote>
<div>
<div>
<div data-smartmail="gmail_signature">
<div>
<div>
<div>
<div>
<div>
<div>
<div>
<div><i>Metrics should not be reduced to simple numeric indicators, to avoid reproducing in the research software world the negative effect&nbsp;</i><i>that bibliographic indicators have had in the research publishing world. It is necessary to bring together a broad spectrum of expertise, and include in the conversation representatives of the research community that will be directly impacted by the creation of these metrics.</i></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</blockquote>
<div>
<div data-smartmail="gmail_signature">
<div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div>By working together, we can build a culture that truly values and respects software as a key part of research, ensuring that credit is fair, thoughtful, and reflective of the complexity of collaboration.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</div>
</div>
<div>
<div>
<div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/05/07/software-heritage-citation-feature/">Software Heritage Citation Feature: Addressing researcher needs</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The OSPO-RADAR Project: Making research software easier to find and use</title>
		<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/04/02/ospo-radar-project-launch/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicole Martinelli]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 13:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[announcement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Codemeta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Open Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OSPO-Radar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sloan Foundation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.softwareheritage.org/?p=45282</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>OSPO-RADAR aims to solve isolated research code issues by building a platform to map, reveal, and make code accessible.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/04/02/ospo-radar-project-launch/">The OSPO-RADAR Project: Making research software easier to find and use</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>By Morane Gruenpeter, Head of Open Science</em></p>



<p>Universities and labs generate a lot of code, but it&#8217;s often hard to find and access. Software Heritage&#8217;s latest initiative, OSPO-RADAR, seeks to address this challenge by creating a platform that maps, reveals, and makes research code more accessible.</p>



<p>An Alfred P. Sloan Foundation grant is making the two-year project possible. This project, full name: Open Source Program Office Research Assets Dashboard and Archival Resource, focuses on developing a platform that supports Open Source Program Offices (OSPOs) at research institutions. The aim is to improve how research software is managed, archived, and showcased, working to raise the profile of research software so it&#8217;s seen as a key part of research.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“Open-source software development is an essential piece of the science ecosystem that drives and sustains scientific discovery,” said Joshua M. Greenberg, Program Director, <a href="https://sloan.org/">Sloan Foundation</a>.&nbsp; “Software Heritage’s OSPO-RADAR project will make visible that influence by giving research institutions a set of tools to better manage, document, and share their open-source work.”</p>
</blockquote>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Scanning the landscape: OSPO challenges and solutions</h2>



<p>OSPOs play a critical role in facilitating open-source software development and adoption in academic and research environments. However, they often face challenges in effectively managing and showcasing their institution&#8217;s software contributions.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">OSPO-RADAR has three core objectives:</h3>



<p><strong>Develop an institutional portal</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>This portal will be built on the foundation of Software Heritage archive integration.</li>



<li>Create a &#8220;Software Assets Dashboard&#8221; service, an institutional portal designed to provide OSPOs with improved metadata management capabilities.</li>



<li>Offer streamlined workflows for OSPOs, simplifying the processes of archiving, managing, and documenting software assets.</li>



<li>Potentially increase institutional visibility, allowing organizations to showcase their open-source software contributions to a wider audience.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Build on the CodeMeta standard</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2020/03/18/codemeta-community/">CodeMeta</a> enhances research software descriptions via semantic metadata. It offers tools like a schema.org vocabulary and interoperability crosswalks. Software Heritage provides the CodeMeta generator for easy metadata integration.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Adapt the CodeMeta standard to address the specific requirements of OSPOs, with ongoing development and maintenance of the CodeMeta generator.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Establish a dedicated Open Science helpdesk</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Provide training materials, resources, and community engagement events to help OSPOs use the portal and its features.</li>
</ul>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/nasa-Q1p7bh3SHj8-unsplash-scaled.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="681" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/nasa-Q1p7bh3SHj8-unsplash-1024x681.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45364" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/nasa-Q1p7bh3SHj8-unsplash-1024x681.jpg 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/nasa-Q1p7bh3SHj8-unsplash-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/nasa-Q1p7bh3SHj8-unsplash-768x511.jpg 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/nasa-Q1p7bh3SHj8-unsplash-1536x1022.jpg 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/nasa-Q1p7bh3SHj8-unsplash-2048x1363.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Photo by NASA on Unsplash.</figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Pinpointing impact</h2>



<p>The OSPO-RADAR project has the potential to impact the research community by:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Elevating research software: By providing tools for managing and showcasing research software, the project will contribute to its recognition as a first-class research output.</li>



<li>Promoting evidence-based development: The project&#8217;s emphasis on metadata management and institutional visibility will enable an evidence-based approach to software development, fostering greater transparency and reproducibility.</li>



<li>Fostering a sustainable ecosystem: By supporting OSPOs, the project will contribute to a more sustainable ecosystem for open-source software management within research institutions.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Get involved</h2>



<p>Software Heritage is collaborating with the <a href="http://CURIOSS.org">CURIOSS</a> network, a community for university and research institution OSPOs.&nbsp; Additionally, we&#8217;re actively seeking academic OSPOs to join us and contribute through the Archives and Libraries Interest Group Members (<a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/support/members-alig/">ALIG</a>) membership. If your organization has an OSPO and you&#8217;re interested in helping us make research software more accessible, we&#8217;d love to hear from you.</p>



<p>To learn more and stay involved, keep an eye on the <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/blog/">Software Heritage blog</a> and our <a href="https://gitlab.softwareheritage.org">GitLab</a> for updates and opportunities to contribute.</p>



<p>Software Heritage&#8217;s involvement in this Sloan Foundation-funded project aligns with our mission to preserve and make accessible the source code of all software. By integrating with the institutional portal, we aim to ensure that research software is not only preserved but also discoverable and reusable.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">About the Author</h2>



<p>Morane Gruenpeter, Head of Open Science, is the Co-Principal Investigator of the OSPO-RADAR Project with Software Heritage co-founder Roberto Di Cosmo. She joined the Software Heritage team in 2017 while finishing a Master’s degree in Computer Science at the University Pierre et Marie Curie. As part of Software Heritage Open Science activities, she&#8217;s the main contact for the SCOSS fundraising campaign and Open Science partnerships, managing various collaborations with organizations such as the CCSD-HAL-Episciences, IPOL, eLife, Zenodo-InvenioRDM, SwMath, Dagstuhl, and others.</p>



<p>She co-chairs several working groups and initiatives for Open Science, including the CodeMeta initiative, the EOSC Opportunity Area OA7 for Research Software, and the Research Data Alliance’s Software Source Code Interest Group, and is an active member of the SciCodes consortium. Her responsibilities span multiple Horizon Europe projects, including FAIRCORE4EOSC and FAIR-IMPACT.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2025/04/02/ospo-radar-project-launch/">The OSPO-RADAR Project: Making research software easier to find and use</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Features in the CodeMeta Generator</title>
		<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/2024/08/30/codemeta-new-features/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marla da Silva]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 15:07:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Codemeta]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.softwareheritage.org/?p=40199</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>At Software Heritage, the universal source code archive, metadata is the software’s identity card. It provides information that can be used to identify, describe and curate software. To make it...</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2024/08/30/codemeta-new-features/">New Features in the CodeMeta Generator</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="part" data-startline="8" data-endline="8">At Software Heritage, the universal source code archive, metadata is the software’s identity card. It provides information that can be used to identify, describe and curate software. To make it easier for users to discover software projects among the millions we archive, having accurate metadata is crucial.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="10" data-endline="10">However, there are many different ways for discribing software and capturing this metadata. <strong>To ensure uniformity and consistency in descriptive metadata</strong>, <strong>Software Heritage has adopted the <a href="https://codemeta.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CodeMeta format</a></strong> as discussed in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2020/03/18/codemeta-community/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this article</a>. The CodeMeta vocabulary is used when indexing metadata and it is recommended to include a codemeta.json file in all research software repositories to make their metadata machine-readable and easily discoverable.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="12" data-endline="12">We recognize the immense value of effectively describing software projects, and we are excited to share the latest developments in the CodeMeta vocabulary and the CodeMeta generator tool.</p>
<h3>A recap: What is CodeMeta?</h3>
<p class="part" data-startline="15" data-endline="15">There are numerous metadata vocabularies for describing software projects. CodeMeta addresses this complexity by providing a standardized “Rosetta stone” for translating between different vocabularies. The vocabulary is an extension of&nbsp;<a href="http://schema.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Schema.org</a>. <strong>CodeMeta allows software metadata to be represented in a consistent JSON format, known as codemeta.json.</strong></p>
<h2>From CodeMeta v2.0 to CodeMeta v3.0</h2>
<p class="part" data-startline="30" data-endline="30">The CodeMeta description format is constantly evolving, in order to meet the needs of the research software ecosystem and scholarly infrastructures users as closely as possible. In 2023, version 3.0 has been published, adding the following new vocabulary elements:</p>
<ul class="part" data-startline="31" data-endline="35">
<li class="" data-startline="31" data-endline="31"><code>review</code>, which allows you to give&nbsp;<a href="https://schema.org/Review" target="_blank" rel="noopener">review information</a>&nbsp;about the software, in this case&nbsp;<code>reviewAspect</code>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<code>reviewBody</code>.</li>
<li class="" data-startline="32" data-endline="32"><code>role</code>, which, associated with an&nbsp;<code>author</code>&nbsp;or a&nbsp;<code>contributor</code>, allows you to define the function (<code>roleName</code>) that this person has held, and for what period of time (<code>startDate</code>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<code>endDate</code>).</li>
<li class="" data-startline="33" data-endline="33"><code>hasSourceCode</code>&nbsp;adding a link that states where the software code is for a given software.</li>
<li class="" data-startline="34" data-endline="35"><code>isSourceCodeOf</code>&nbsp;adding a link that states where software application is built from a given source code. This is the reverse property of ‘hasSourceCode’.</li>
</ul>
<p class="part" data-startline="36" data-endline="36">Some properties also changed name for clarification:</p>
<ul class="part" data-startline="37" data-endline="39">
<li class="" data-startline="37" data-endline="37"><code>contIntegration</code>&nbsp;became&nbsp;<code>continuousIntegration</code></li>
<li class="" data-startline="38" data-endline="39"><code>embargoDate</code>&nbsp;became&nbsp;<code>embargoEndDate</code></li>
</ul>
<p class="part" data-startline="40" data-endline="40">Just as there are translation files between different metadata description formats, there is&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/codemeta/codemeta/blob/master/crosswalks/codemeta-V2.csv" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the translation file</a>&nbsp;from format v2.0 to format v3.0.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="42" data-endline="42">You can find&nbsp;<a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/codemeta/codemeta/master/codemeta.json" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an example</a>&nbsp;of CodeMeta v3.0 for the codemeta project.</p>
<h2>Features of the CodeMeta generator</h2>
<p class="part" data-startline="46" data-endline="46">Software Heritage maintains a tool for helping users to create the corresponding&nbsp;<code>codemeta.json</code>&nbsp;file, the&nbsp;<a href="https://codemeta.github.io/codemeta-generator/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CodeMeta generator</a>. It consists of a simple form that users can fill in to generate a valid file. This file can then be added at the root of the software code repository.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="48" data-endline="48">Additionally, the generator now supports creating codemeta.json files in both v2.0 and v3.0 formats, and the form has been redesigned to include new functionalities, such as the Review box and role management.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="50" data-endline="50">The form has been reorganized, to include the new Review box.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="52" data-endline="52"><img decoding="async" class="" src="https://hedgedoc.softwareheritage.org/uploads/394fcb3e-cbb0-4dc6-868e-3ba8c68f0e14.png" alt=""></p>
<p class="part" data-startline="54" data-endline="54"><em>The new Review box</em></p>
<p class="part" data-startline="56" data-endline="56">You can now add roles to authors and contributors.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="58" data-endline="58"><img decoding="async" class="" src="https://hedgedoc.softwareheritage.org/uploads/2887789f-c6ee-4bdd-8eee-b8d7100417a5.png" alt=""></p>
<p class="part" data-startline="60" data-endline="60"><em>The new Role functionnality</em></p>
<p class="part" data-startline="62" data-endline="62">License(s) field values are suggested and completed from the SPDX licences list.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="64" data-endline="64"><img decoding="async" class="" src="https://hedgedoc.softwareheritage.org/uploads/58f6c254-639c-4ab2-9011-f509364074e4.png" alt=""></p>
<p class="part" data-startline="66" data-endline="66"><em>The SPDX licence list suggestions</em></p>
<p class="part" data-startline="68" data-endline="68">That is not all: you can import an already existing&nbsp;<code>codemeta.json</code>&nbsp;file (in v2.0 or v3.0). The form will be updated with the values found in the&nbsp;<code>codemeta.json</code>&nbsp;text area (where you pasted your file).</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="70" data-endline="70">Finally, a little cherry on top, you can directly download the file from the tool!</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="72" data-endline="72"><img decoding="async" class="" src="https://hedgedoc.softwareheritage.org/uploads/dd0232cd-d149-4d9c-8a87-0f20d9b0914b.png" alt=""></p>
<p class="part" data-startline="74" data-endline="74"><em>CodeMeta generator actions</em></p>
<h2>Metadata for citation</h2>
<p class="part" data-startline="78" data-endline="78">With the latest advancements in software metadata, you will soon have the ability to cite source code directly from the Software Heritage archive in BibTeX format, making it easier to reference software in academic work.</p>
<h2>Get Involved with CodeMeta!</h2>
<p class="part" data-startline="81" data-endline="81">The CodeMeta project is an evolving community-driven initiative. We invite developers, researchers, and enthusiasts to join&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/codemeta/codemeta/discussions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">discussions</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/codemeta/codemeta-generator/issues/new/choose" target="_blank" rel="noopener">suggest changes</a>, or&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/codemeta/codemeta-generator/pulls" target="_blank" rel="noopener">contribute Pull Requests directly</a>&nbsp;to the CodeMeta generator on GitHub. By collaborating, we can continue to improve the tool and advance software metadata practices worldwide.</p>
<p class="part" data-startline="83" data-endline="83"><strong><em>Stay updated on the latest developments by following our contributions and announcements!</em></strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2024/08/30/codemeta-new-features/">New Features in the CodeMeta Generator</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Deep Dive into the archival of Software Metadata</title>
		<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/2023/08/24/archival-of-software-metadata/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marla da Silva]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 13:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Codemeta]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.softwareheritage.org/?p=36044</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Software metadata is vital for the classification, curation, and sharing of free and open-source software (FOSS). In a recent presentation at the Software Heritage Ambassador&#8217;s plenary, Morane Gruenpeter and Valentin...</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2023/08/24/archival-of-software-metadata/">Deep Dive into the archival of Software Metadata</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Software metadata is vital for the classification, curation, and sharing of free and open-source software (FOSS). In a recent presentation at the Software Heritage Ambassador&#8217;s plenary, <a href="https://twitter.com/moraneottilia" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morane Gruenpeter</a> and Valentin Lorentz discussed the collection, preservation, and sharing of software metadata to build the semantic web of FOSS.</p>
<p>Software Heritage <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/mission/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">aims to collect, preserve and share the software commons from various sources</a>, with the goal of creating the universal source code archive. Currently, the archive holds over 251 million projects and more than 16 billion unique source code files. However, since the same source code can be collected from different origins, there can be variations in the accompanying metadata, which describe the projects.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft wp-image-36045 size-full" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/archive.png" alt="" width="2254" height="904" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/archive.png 2254w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/archive-300x120.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/archive-1024x411.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/archive-768x308.png 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/archive-1536x616.png 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/archive-2048x821.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2254px) 100vw, 2254px" /></a></p>
<h3>Navigating the metadata maze</h3>
<p>To navigate this diverse source code landscape, relevant metadata becomes crucial. Different projects may use different terms, vocabularies, and ontologies to describe themselves. By generating linked data and referencing source code artifacts within the Software Heritage archive, there is potential to create a &#8220;semantic Wikipedia&#8221; of software.</p>
<p>Analyzing the existing metadata landscape reveals various sources, including catalogues, repositories, platforms, and package managers like <a href="https://ascl.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ASCL</a>, <a href="https://zbmath.org/software/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">swMath</a>, <a href="https://www.openaire.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OpenAire</a>, <a href="https://libraries.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">libraries.io</a>, <a href="https://zenodo.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zenodo</a>, <a href="https://hal.science/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">HAL</a>, <a href="https://github.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub</a>, <a href="https://pypi.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PyPI</a>, <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NPM</a> and many more.</p>
<h2>There are two sources of extraction for metadata, which can be either intrinsic or extrinsic to the source code</h2>
<h3>The embbeded metadata, a.k.a intrinsic metadata</h3>
<p>Intrinsic metadata refers to information within the source code itself, such as README files, licenses, and package management files. It can be human-readable (README) or machine-actionable (codemeta.json), offering accuracy and longevity but relying on the author&#8217;s knowledge.</p>
<p>An example of a human-readable file, a README file, from the Parmap software project: <a href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:cnt:43243e2ae91a64e252170cd922718e8c2af323b6;origin=https://github.com/rdicosmo/parmap;visit=swh:1:snp:e4b14ad0619db71bb86ebac7edc7c6c8ab234ee9;anchor=swh:1:rev:963608763589e03de38e744d359884d491e65460;path=/README.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener">swh:1:cnt:43243e2ae91a64e252170cd922718e8c2af323b6</a></p>
<p><a href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/browse/content/sha1_git:43243e2ae91a64e252170cd922718e8c2af323b6/?origin_url=https://github.com/rdicosmo/parmap&amp;path=README.md&amp;revision=963608763589e03de38e744d359884d491e65460&amp;snapshot=e4b14ad0619db71bb86ebac7edc7c6c8ab234ee9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-36062 size-large" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/readme-1024x586.png" alt="" width="1024" height="586" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/readme-1024x586.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/readme-300x172.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/readme-768x440.png 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/readme-1536x879.png 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/readme-2048x1172.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></p>
<p>An example of a machine-actionable metadata file, a codemeta.json file, from the Parmap software project:<br />
<a href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:cnt:0be13d6d1d0c0b377cd6e9e152d24c4e0b08d37d;origin=https://github.com/rdicosmo/parmap;visit=swh:1:snp:e4b14ad0619db71bb86ebac7edc7c6c8ab234ee9;anchor=swh:1:rev:963608763589e03de38e744d359884d491e65460;path=/codemeta.json" target="_blank" rel="noopener">swh:1:cnt:0be13d6d1d0c0b377cd6e9e152d24c4e0b08d37d</a></p>
<p><a href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/browse/content/sha1_git:0be13d6d1d0c0b377cd6e9e152d24c4e0b08d37d/?origin_url=https://github.com/rdicosmo/parmap&amp;path=codemeta.json&amp;revision=963608763589e03de38e744d359884d491e65460&amp;snapshot=e4b14ad0619db71bb86ebac7edc7c6c8ab234ee9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-36074" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/browse-1024x586.png" alt="" width="1024" height="586" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/browse-1024x586.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/browse-300x172.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/browse-768x440.png 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/browse-1536x879.png 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/browse-2048x1172.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a><br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-36077" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/codemetadata-1024x499.png" alt="" width="1024" height="499" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/codemetadata-1024x499.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/codemetadata-300x146.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/codemetadata-768x374.png 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/codemetadata-1536x749.png 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/codemetadata-2048x998.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<h3>The external metadata, a.k.a extrinsic metadata</h3>
<p>Extrinsic metadata refers to metadata records on external entities like code hosting platforms, registries or scholarly repositories keeping additional information about the Software. Curating the software source code&#8217;s metadata while archiving it is a good approach to ensure accuracy and completeness. For example, the HAL French national archive provides a moderation workflow to verify the metadata compatibility with the software artifacts. Below you can see a full metadata record as captured on the <a href="https://hal.science/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">HAL</a> platform:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-36080" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hal-1024x519.png" alt="" width="1024" height="519" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hal-1024x519.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hal-300x152.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hal-768x389.png 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hal-1536x779.png 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hal-2048x1038.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>For more information about the HAL-SWH integration, you can read the <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2023/04/04/swhid-deposit-hal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blog post</a> and watch the <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2023/04/04/swhid-deposit-hal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tutorials</a>.</p>
<h3>Translating metadata with CodeMeta</h3>
<p>The CodeMeta vocabulary, a subset of schema.org, facilitates interoperability and consistency in software metadata. It acts as a common vocabulary, and the community is encouraged to contribute to the discussion in the CodeMeta repository.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s key addition is the crosswalk table that provides mappings to many software vocabularies. With the CodeMeta crosswalk table, indexing becomes possible.</p>
<h3>Unravelling the Process: From Collection to Indexing</h3>
<p>Behind the scenes, there is a well-oiled machine that facilitates the storage and indexing of metadata, enabling search possibilities and promoting the discoverability of software.</p>
<p>In this system, two types of metadata are managed. The first type, intrinsic metadata, is stored alongside the code in the main storage. The second type, extrinsic metadata, is archived separately in the Raw Extrinsic Metadata Storage.</p>
<p>To effectively index the metadata, a translator is utilized to convert it into CodeMeta format. The resulting indexed metadata is then stored in a dedicated location called the Indexed Metadata Storage.</p>
<p>For a more comprehensive understanding of this workflow, you can refer to <a href="https://docs.softwareheritage.org/devel/swh-indexer/metadata-workflow.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Software Heritage&#8217;s documentation</a>.</p>
<p>Below is a diagram depicting the complete workflow, encompassing the steps to collect, preserve, index, and share metadata:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-36083" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/metadata-flow-1024x736.png" alt="" width="1024" height="736" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/metadata-flow-1024x736.png 1024w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/metadata-flow-300x216.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/metadata-flow-768x552.png 768w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/metadata-flow-1536x1105.png 1536w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/metadata-flow-1000x720.png 1000w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/metadata-flow.png 1894w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<p>By following this workflow, the system can efficiently manage and make accessible the metadata associated with various software, helping in the discovery and sharing of valuable code and related information.</p>
<h3>The metadata use cases on the Software Heritage web-app</h3>
<p>Presenting software metadata effectively on web interfaces is crucial. Intrinsic and extrinsic metadata, as well as specific properties like citations, need to be showcased. Software Heritage&#8217;s roadmap includes plans for metadata presentation.</p>
<p>One of the key principles of Software Heritage is to include and present only &#8220;facts&#8221; in its knowledge base. However, this principle becomes challenging when dealing with metadata due to the subjective nature of such information. Translating metadata semantically, in order to harmonize the diversity, can also introduce qualitative interpretation issues. Mapping terms and information can be susceptible to misinterpretation and loss of meaning during the translation process.</p>
<p>For example, in Python PKG-INFO, there are two properties `summary` and `description` that are mapped to the `description` property in the CodeMeta crosswalk table. This is not the only example where vocabularies introduce different and yet similar terms to semantically describe different aspects.</p>
<p>In the coming months, we will collect use cases from the community to better understand the software metadata needs.</p>
<p>You are invited to share your use case via the issues on the *<a href="https://gitlab.softwareheritage.org/swh/use-cases" target="_blank" rel="noopener">use cases repository</a>* to facilitate analysis of these use cases by the SWH team.</p>
<p>We hope that the collaborative efforts of the Software Heritage community and user involvement will lead to a more interconnected and discoverable FOSS ecosystem.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2023/08/24/archival-of-software-metadata/">Deep Dive into the archival of Software Metadata</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Software Heritage contributes CodeMeta generator to the community</title>
		<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/2020/03/18/codemeta-community/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Morane Gruenpeter]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 14:25:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Codemeta]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.softwareheritage.org/?p=21219</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Software projects are a precious part of our technical, scientific and organisational knowledge, and that&#8217;s why Software Heritage&#8217;s mission is to collect, preserve and share all their source code. In...</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2020/03/18/codemeta-community/">Software Heritage contributes CodeMeta generator to the community</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Software projects are a precious part of our technical, scientific and organisational knowledge, and that&#8217;s why Software Heritage&#8217;s mission is to collect, preserve and share all their source code.</p>
<p>In order to make it easy to discover the software projects you may be interested in, among the <a href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tens of millions</a> that we archive, it is important to have proper metadata that describes them. This is why we are spending significant energy to connect with several communities that work on software metadata.</p>
<p>Today, we are happy to share a significant contribution we are making to one of these communities, <a href="https://codemeta.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CodeMeta</a>, by releasing to the public a new tool, the <a href="https://codemeta.github.io/codemeta-generator/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CodeMeta generator</a>, that allows to easily create or edit metadata files conforming to the CodeMeta schema.</p>
<h2>What is CodeMeta?</h2>
<p>There are (too) many different metadata vocabularies out there: some are used for describing packages and their dependencies, other are used in Wikidata, others in various ontologies. The picture below presents just a little fraction of the complex landscape you are confronted with when looking for a way to describe a software project.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft wp-image-18140 size-full" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1.png" alt="" width="810" height="392" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1.png 810w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1-300x145.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1-768x372.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 810px) 100vw, 810px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The CodeMeta project started an effort to address this issue, and led to the development of a sort of Rosetta stone for translating from one vocabulary to the other: <a href="https://codemeta.github.io/crosswalk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the CodeMeta crosswalk table</a>.</p>
<p>An important offspring of this effort is the creation of the CodeMeta vocabulary, as an extension of the SoftwareApplication and SoftwareSourceCode classes found in the vocabulary of the popular <a href="https://schema.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Schema.org</a> initiative. Metadata information conformant to the CodeMeta vocabulary can be represented in JSON format, typically named codemeta.json.</p>
<h2>CodeMeta at Software Heritage</h2>
<p>Here at Software Heritage, we decided early on to use the CodeMeta vocabulary internally when <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2019/05/28/mining-software-metadata-for-80-m-projects-and-even-more/?lang=fr" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">indexing intrinsic metadata</a>, and joined the <a href="https://github.com/force11/force11-sciwg/blob/master/CodeMeta_Task_Force.md">CodeMeta task force in FORCE11</a> that is now stewarding the inclusion of the CodeMeta vocabulary into the schema.org vocabulary.</p>
<p>We also joined a growing consensus in the academic community by recommending to add a codemeta.json file to all research software repositories in our <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/save-and-reference-research-software/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">guidelines for saving and referencing research software</a>: indeed, embarking a codemeta.json in a software repository is a simple and effective way to make your metadata accessible in a machine readable form, hence easily indexable in Software Heritage.</p>
<p>More recently we adopted the CodeMeta representation, in the form of codemeta.json files, for describing landmark legacy software in the framework of <a href="http://www.softwareheritage.org/swhap" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SWHAP, the Software Heritage Acquisition Process</a>, developed in collaboration with the University of Pisa and UNESCO .</p>
<h2>The CodeMeta generator is here!</h2>
<p>The need emerged clearly for a tool to easily create a new CodeMeta file or edit an existing one, and since no such tool was available, we decided to dedicate some of the Software Heritage engineering resources to develop it. A first prototype was showcased at the the <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2019/10/23/research-software-hackathon-at-force2019/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">FORCE2019 Hackathon</a> a few months ago.</p>
<p>Today, we&#8217;re delighted to share the news that the repository of the CodeMeta generator has been moved under the <a href="https://codemeta.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CodeMeta</a> umbrella, released under the AGPL licence, and you can collaborate to its evolution right now on <a href="https://github.com/codemeta/codemeta-generator/"> its repository</a>.</p>
<p>The tool is implemented as a serverless web application, so you can run the tool locally on your browser, or use the <a href="https://codemeta.github.io/codemeta-generator/">online version</a> hosted on the CodeMeta website, with no fear of overloading it.</p>
<p>Try it, and we&#8217;re confident all your software projects will soon have a machine readable codemeta.json too!</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2020/03/18/codemeta-community/">Software Heritage contributes CodeMeta generator to the community</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mining software metadata for 80 M projects and even more</title>
		<link>https://www.softwareheritage.org/2019/05/28/mining-software-metadata-for-80-m-projects-and-even-more/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Valentin Lorentz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2019 06:08:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Codemeta]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.softwareheritage.org/?p=18086</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You can now search archived source code by project metadata. Navigating through the vast amount of source code archived by Software Heritage can be daunting, and we are working to...</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2019/05/28/mining-software-metadata-for-80-m-projects-and-even-more/">Mining software metadata for 80 M projects and even more</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3><strong>You can now search archived source code by project metadata.</strong></h3>
<p>Navigating through the vast amount of source code archived by Software Heritage can be daunting, and we are working to provide appropriate tools to search inside it. As a first step in this direction, we have been providing you with the possibility to search among the tens of millions of URLs where the source code comes from. This is already quite useful, as these URLs usually contain the project name as well as the name of the hosting organization, but we want more.</p>
<p>The next step has been to make software metadata searchable too. This metadata is extracted from packaging information (as contained in, e.g., package.json, pom.xml, etc.), and is particularly interesting because it is curated by software authors and distributed via forges or repositories, together with the source code.</p>
<p>We are happy to announce that&nbsp; metadata-based search is now available for Software Heritage.</p>
<p>Here is an example: suppose we&#8217;re looking for the project where Julien Danjou is involved. Now we can just go to <a href="https://archive.softwareheritage.org/browse/search/">Software Heritage&#8217;s search page</a>, type the name in the search bar, tick the &#8220;search in metadata&#8221; box, press Enter, and we find what we are looking for:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_search_Julien_Danjou.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-18145" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_search_Julien_Danjou.png" alt="screenshot of the metadata search for 'Julien Danjou', showing his projects on PyPI: pymunincli, pifpaf, etc." width="680" height="660" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_search_Julien_Danjou.png 680w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_search_Julien_Danjou-300x291.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /></a></p>
<h2>Addressing the metadata heterogeneity challenge.</h2>
<p>It seems quite easy, right? But it was actually quite complex to do, because the landscape of software ontologies and metadata standards is quite vast. Various communities have produced different ontologies and vocabularies to describe software and software source code, and different packaging system tend to use different ones.<a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-18140 aligncenter" src="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1.png" alt="" width="810" height="392" srcset="https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1.png 810w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1-300x145.png 300w, https://www.softwareheritage.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/metadata_landscape_RDA11-metadata_landscape_final1-768x372.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 810px) 100vw, 810px" /></a></p>
<p>Due to the heterogeneity of the source code archived in Software Heritage, we needed a common vocabulary that encompasses the largest possible amount of software metadata that can be found in the archive, and we wanted to avoid introducing yet another one.</p>
<p>Luckily, this exact problem has been adressed already by the CodeMeta initiative, whose <a href="https://codemeta.github.io/crosswalk/">crosswalk table</a> is a kind of Rosetta stone for translating software metadata terminology back and forth into a single vocabulary that is a refinement of the <a class="remarkup-link" href="https://schema.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">schema.org</a> classes SoftwareApplication and SoftwareSourceCode, providuing a convenient bridge with linked data and the semantic web.</p>
<h2>Under the hood</h2>
<p>For those of you that are curious about the technical implementation, here is an overview of how all this works. We have created an asynchronous metadata indexing mechanism that sifts through the whole archive for metadata in formats that we can translate to CodeMeta.</p>
<p>For each software origin in the archive, we take its most recent visit and look for the root directory of its &#8220;HEAD&#8221; revision. If there is a file whose name indicates it is a metadata file (according to filename-based heuristics that can be extended over time), we fetch it, and feed it to the <a href="https://docs.softwareheritage.org/devel/swh-indexer/metadata-workflow.html#supported-intrinsic-metadata" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">appropriate metadata translator</a>. The resulting (CodeMeta) metadata are stored in a database which can then be queried at search time.</p>
<p>Each metadata translator reads the input file as a dictionary, translates key names following the crosswalk table provided by the CodeMeta Project, and normalizes the results.<br />
For instance, the translator for <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NPM</a> metadata applies the following steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>read a <code>package.json</code> file</li>
<li>decode the JSON into a Python dictionary</li>
<li>translate each key using the <a href="https://github.com/codemeta/codemeta/blob/5b77c0fba3774b84c921ee8168bf46c99c999352/crosswalks/NodeJS.csv">crosswalk table for NPM</a></li>
<li>parse/normalize values from NPM&#8217;s specific format into the structure expected by CodeMeta</li>
<li>convert the obtained dictionary to a CodeMeta object</li>
</ol>
<p>Only step 4 is specific to NPM, the other ones are shared between all metadata translators. The code to normalize each field is usually rather short, given that it is already designed to be machine-readable. Excluding comments, the NPM metadata translator is only 75 lines of code long,&nbsp; with more than half of the code dedicated to handling the <code>bugs</code> and <code>author</code> fields, which need a more complex handling because they allow more flexible formats.</p>
<p>The currently <a href="https://docs.softwareheritage.org/devel/swh-indexer/metadata-workflow.html#supported-intrinsic-metadata" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">supported metadata</a> formats are the following: Maven&#8217;s pom.xml, NPM&#8217;s package.json, Python&#8217;s PKG-INFO, and Ruby&#8217;s gemspec.</p>
<p>This is just a starting point, and we welcome contributions to support additional metadata formats. We have made available <a href="https://docs.softwareheritage.org/devel/swh-indexer/metadata-workflow.html#adding-support-for-additional-ecosystem-specific-metadata">a tutorial on how to add support for additional metadata formats</a>. Thanks to the CodeMeta crosswalk table, there is actually very little you need to do to add support for your preferred format; the NPM translator&#8217;s core looks like this:</p>
<pre class="brush: python; title: ; notranslate">
class NpmMapping(DictMapping, SingleFileMapping):
    # load the crosswalk table for NodeJS:
    mapping = CROSSWALK_TABLE&#x5B;&#039;NodeJS&#039;]

    # Define what filename to look for:
    filename = b&#039;package.json&#039;

    # Define which fields we want to read:
    string_fields = &#x5B;&#039;name&#039;, &#039;version&#039;, &#039;homepage&#039;,
                     &#039;description&#039;, &#039;email&#039;]

    def translate(self, raw_content):
        # Decode the input bytes to a text string:
        raw_content = raw_content.decode()

        # Load the text string as a JSON object/dictionary:
        content_dict = json.loads(raw_content)

        # convert the JSON object/dictionary to CodeMeta:
        return self._translate_dict(content_dict)
</pre>
<p><a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/community/developers/">Contribute to the Software Heritage development effort</a> &nbsp;by adding support for additional metadata formats!</p>
<hr>
<p style="text-align: right;">— by Morane Gruenpeter and Valentin Lorentz</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org/2019/05/28/mining-software-metadata-for-80-m-projects-and-even-more/">Mining software metadata for 80 M projects and even more</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.softwareheritage.org">Software Heritage</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
